-==www.RagBear.com==- 是, 首相  第2季第7集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=- 翻译: hj6093 校对&时间轴: tpring
国民教育
组织秘书和党主席想见您
The Chief Whip and Party Chairman to see you.
各位请坐 我马上就好
Take a seat. I'll be right with you.
伯纳 坐下 我要你也列席
Bernard, take a seat.I want you here for this meeting.
这不是党派事务吗? 这是党派主席和组织秘书
Isn't this a party matter?
也是政府工作
It's also a government matter.
是我们的教育政策      国家的还是党派的?
It's about our education policy.The government's or party's?
都一样      抱歉 首相 这可大不一样
It's the same thing.With respect, they're not the same thing.
所以才要开会讨论      好像是党派...
That's why we want the meeting.It seems...
伯纳 坐下
Bernard... sit!
不许动
Stay.
问题在哪里?
What's the problem?
教育      你觉得我能怎么办?
Education.What can I do about it?
您是首相啊      对 我知道
You're the PM.Yes, I know.
我没法直接插手教育事务
I have no direct control over education.
我管不了课程 考试 教务长任命 什么都管不了
I don't control the curriculum or exams. Nothing.
可选民觉得都该您负责 您影响力大嘛
The voters hold you responsible for everything.
我烦透了 我原以为当了首相
I'm fed up with it. When I became PM, I thought
就大权在握 结果得到什么? 影响力
I'd have power. And what have I got? Influence.
我控制不了警察 利率
I've got no power over the police, the rates,
欧共体指令 欧洲法庭 我们的法庭 法官 北约
EEC directives, European courts, our courts, the judges, NATO.
我到底有什么权力?
What have I got the power to do?
让我们输掉下次大选的权力
Lose us the next election.
您再不管管教育 它就立竿见影了
Which you will if you don't tackle education.
选民们希望管管学术浮夸 学风懒散
The voters want something done about low academic attainment.
性教育      我不是反对性教育
Sex education!I'm not against sex education.
我不是反对课堂上教育孩子生命的真谛
I'm not against children being taught the facts of life in class,
但不能教他们同性恋的技巧啊
but not homosexual technique!
当然 异性恋的技巧也不行      那他们去哪学呢?
Or heterosexual technique.Where should they learn it?
在自行车棚后面 像我们当年一样
Behind the bike sheds like we did!
你是吗?
Did you?
别去管性技巧了
Never mind sexual technique.
有些学校教印度语比教英文还多
Some of our schools are teaching more Hindi than English.
我知道英语更重要 但我不敢公开说
I know English is more important, but I daren't say so
会被人扣上种族主义帽子的
or I'd be accused of racism.
对 可...      上次接见民族事务委员会
When I met the Ethnic Awareness Council,
一位黑人女代表发言时
I happened to glance at my watch
我凑巧看了看表
when a black woman delegate was speaking
马上被指责一举一动充满种族歧视
and I was accused of racist body language.
还有性别歧视
And sexist.
好吧 你们要我怎么办?      请您狠抓教育
What do you want me to do? Get a grip on education.
让亨利把他的教育部好好整治一番
Get Henry to do something about the Department of Education.
不行 他已经给驯服了      开掉他
They've got him house-trained. Sack him.
我不能再来一次内阁动乱了
I can't have another Cabinet convulsion.
那就请在野党党魁夫人来吧      她来干嘛?
Then invite the opposition leader's wife here. What can she do?
量尺寸准备换地毯和窗帘
Start measuring up for carpets and curtains.
好 没问题 今天下午吗?
Yes, right, fine. This afternoon?
伯纳 首相似乎要见我      是的 汉弗莱爵士
Bernard, I believe the PM wants to see me. Yes, Sir Humphrey.
他有什么问题?      教育
What's his problem? Education.
这个嘛 现在后悔也晚了
Well, it's a bit late to do anything about that now.
不 是教育系统问题      我明白了
No, no, the education system. I see.
那个也晚了      他觉得他会输掉下次大选的
late to do about that either. he'll lose the next election.
对国家未必是坏事      他没法忽略事实
Worse things could befall the nation. He can't ignore facts.
如果不能忽略事实 他这政客就不用当了
If he can't ignore facts, he's got no business being a politician.
不管怎样 伯纳 他不必担心
Anyway, Bernard, he's got nothing to worry about.
我们的教育系统满足了大多数家长的要求
The education system does all most parents require of it.
就是家长上班时 帮他们看孩子
Keeps children out of mischief while they're at work.
对 可从党主席给首相的报告来看
That paper the Party Chairman had suggests
综合素质教育快破产了吧?
the comprehensive system is breaking down.
伯纳 我万万想不到
Bernard, I never thought to hear such language
一个忠实的公务员会说出这种话
from a loyal member of the Civil Service!
你被敌人俘虏了吗?        您说俄国人?
Have you been got at by the enemy? You mean the Russians?
不 伯纳 我说首相的政治顾问
No, Bernard, I mean the PM's political advisor
那个叫韦莱的女人
that Wainwright female.
可综合素质教育是个实验 当然需要规制
Comprehensive education ought to be validated.
当然 但不能一棍子打死啊
Of course, but not invalidated.
可如果它是为了提升教育质量...
But if it was introduced to improve standards...
你怎么会有这个念头?
Whatever gave you that idea?
您是说它是用来抹平阶级差异的?      正是
You mean it was to get rid of class distinction? Precisely!
所以孩子们...      孩子?
So that all children... Children?
关孩子什么事?      我以为...
Who mentioned children? I just...
教育部里从来不提孩子
The Department of Education never mentions children!
不不不 伯纳 它是用来抹平
No, no, no, no, Bernard. It was to get rid of
教师的阶级差异的
class distinction in the teaching profession.
提升教师的生活质量
Improve the living standard of teachers,
而不是孩子的教育质量
not the educational standards of children.
提升教师工会会员的工资
Bring the NUT teachers up
让它和他们的死对头
to the salary level of their rivals in
语法学校的全国校长联合会会员持平
the National Association of Schoolmasters in the grammar schools.
可是...      伯纳 工党执政的时候
But the... When there is a Labour government,
教育部夸综合素质教育能抹平阶级差异
the ESD says comprehensives abolish the class system.
等保守党上台 他们就改口夸它价格便宜量又足
When there's Tory, they say it's the cheapest way.
对工党我们解释说 选择性教育造成阶级分化
To Labour, we explain that selective education is divisive
对保守党就解释说 选择性教育贵得离谱
and to the Tories we explain that it is expensive.
这样 我们就能跟教师工会搞好关系
That way, we have a happy relationship with the NUT
关起门来给自家孩子私立教育了
and we educate our own children privately.
但如果政府想改变...      工会不想改变
But if the government wants change... The teaching unions don't.
我们的工作不是说服工会接受政府政策吗?
Isn't it our job to persuade unions to accept government policy?
不 我们的工作是说服政府接受工会政策
No, it is our job to get the government to accept union policy.
因为政府政策说变就变 而工会政策雷打不动
Since government change policy all the time
天经地义的 应该让政府适应工会才对
the government SHOULD be brought in line with the unions.
喂 首相? 好的 他现在就去见您
Yes, PM? Oh, fine. He can see you now.
汉弗莱爵士 他很担心有些事
Sir Humphrey, he's very worried that he seems
他无能为力 也要他负责
responsible for something he can't change.
是啊 那还用说 为无能为力的事负责
Yes, I'm sure. Responsibility without power -
这是每朝每代的太监的特权
the prerogative of the eunuch throughout the ages.
早安 首相      早安 汉弗莱 你说什么?
PM. Good morning. What were you saying?
没什么 首相 听说您在担心地方教育当局
you're worried about the local education authority.
不 汉弗莱 我是担心国家教育部
No, the Department of Education and Science.
是吗? 我觉得教育部干得很好啊
Indeed? I think the DES does a splendid job.
随你怎么说 睁眼看看现状吧
Look what's happened to education.
这是一篇宗教论文的论题
This is a question from a Religious Studies paper.
“你更喜欢哪个——原子弹或慈善事业?”
"Which do you prefer atom bombs or charity?"
连数学题也政治化了
Even maths is politicised.
“如果英国核武防御每年要花5亿英镑”
"If it costs ? billion a yearfor nuclear defences
“喂饱一名非洲饥童每年要75英镑”
"and ?5 a year to feed a starving African child,
“如果国防部放弃核武器”
"how many children could be saved from starvation
“能救多少非洲孩子的命?”
"if the Ministry of Defence abandoned nuclear weapons?"
很简单 零个 他们会拿钱去买常规武器
That's easy. None. They'd spend it all on conventional weapons.
不管怎样 这只是个算术 5亿除以75就行了
In any case, it's just a sum. Five billion divided by 75.
可孩子们也没学会算算数
But children aren't learning to do the sums.
没错 可地方教育当局也许会说
The local education authorities might argue
他们不必 他们有计算器啊
that they don't need to. They have calculators.
他们总得明白原理吧
They all need to know HOW it's done.
我们都学过基本算术 不是吗?
We were all taught basis arithmetic, weren't we?
是吗? 3947除73等于多少?
Were we? What's 3,947 divided by 73?
呃 我需要纸笔打草稿...得了别管了
Er... Oh, I'd need a pencil and paper to do that.
我刚毕业的时候会的      可现在您用计算器了
I could do it when I left school. Now you'd use a calculator.
这不是重点 看看拉丁文 现在没人懂了吧?
That's not the point. Look at Latin. Hardly anybody knows that now.
Tempora mutantur, nos et mutamur in illis.
"Tempora mutantur, nos et mutamur in illis."
什么?
What?
“时间变化 我们随之而变”      一点不错
Times change and we change with the times. Precisely.
Si tacuisses, philosophus manisses
Si tacuisses, philosophus manisses.
什么意思?
What does that mean?
“请你闭嘴 会显得聪明点”
kept your mouth shut, we might thought you were clever.
你说什么?      不是说您 首相 那是翻译
I beg your pardon? Not you, PM. That's the translation.
没人会以为 汉弗莱爵士会那么说您
No one would have thought Sir Humphrey was saying that about you.
走开 伯纳 求你了
Go away, Bernard, please.
真不敢相信 汉弗莱
I can't believe it.
你是受严格学院式教育长大的
You had a strict academic upbringing.
你居然否认它的价值?
Are you denying the value of it?
有什么用呢? 我跟英国首相说话都用不上
I can't even call upon it in conversation with the PM
这个国家的教育是场灾难
Education in this country is a disaster.
我们应该教会孩子谋生 结果却整天让他们无聊
We're supposed to prepare children for work.
我倒觉得 无聊是他们谋生的必备技能
being bored stiff was an excellent preparation for work.
毕业时间提高到16岁了 学的却更少了
The school leaving age was raised to 16, but they're learning less.
我们提高毕业年龄 又不是为了多学
We didn't raise it so they'd learn more
而是为了把青少年拦在就业市场外
but to keep teenagers off the job market
以降低失业率
and hold down unemployment figures.
你难道是说 教育一点问题都没有?
Are you saying there's nothing wrong with education?
当然不是 首相 它是个笑话
Of course not. It's a joke.
一直都是个笑话
It's always been a joke.
在地方政务理事会手里 会永远是个笑话
By leaving it in the hands of local councillors
一半理事是您的敌人
Half of them are your enemies
另一半是朋友 却让您觉得还是敌人好
and the other half make you prefer your enemies.
你想说什么?        我是说 教育永远也好转不了
What are you saying? That education will never get any better
只要它还在市政厅那帮笨蛋手里
as long as it's subject to all that tomfoolery in the town halls.
想想要是把国防交给他们 后果如何
Imagine what would happen if you put defence in their hands.
国防?      对 给每个理事会一亿英镑
Defence? Give councils ?00 million each
叫他们自己搞国防 别担心俄国了
and ask them to defend themselves,
不出三周内战就爆发了
we'd have a civil war in three weeks!
别胡思乱想      是吗? 教育就是活例子
You're being silly. Am I? That's what's happened to education.
为什么? 因为没人会以对待国防
And why? Because nobody thinks education
的认真劲儿来对待教育
is serious the way defence is serious.
这就是为什么民防系统
So that's why civil defence
交给地方政府吧?
is in local authority hands?
当然 因为大家都知道民防是个笑话
Of course. Because everybody knows it's a joke.
反正不能把重要的事交给那些小丑管
don't leave important matters to those clowns!
鉴于您已经把教育丢给他们管
And as you've left education to them,
只能推断 到目前为止 您没有重视它
you have attached little importance to it.
它当然重要 它能让我输掉下次大选啊
It is important. It could lose me the next election.
我还天真地以为 您是担心我们孩子们的未来呢
I thought you were concerned about the future of children.
我也担心呀 毕竟 他们满18岁就能投票了
Yes, that too. After all, they get the vote at 18.
好 首相 那就中央集权吧 把它从地方收上来
Then, PM, then centralise. Take it away from the local councils.
置于教育部掌管下 您就能有所作为了
Put it under the DES, you could do something about it.
你觉得我行吗? 披荆斩棘 牵着牛角走?
Do you think I could? Grasp the nettle, take the bull by the horns?
首相 如果您披荆斩棘 就没法牵牛角了
You can't take the bull by the horns if you're grasping the nettle.
是吗 伯纳?
Oh, really, Bernard?
我是说 您可以一手斩荆棘 一手牵牛角
grasping the nettle, you could take the bull by one horn
但无法牵两个角 因为您的手不够大
but not both horns because your hand isn't big enough.
如果只牵一个角 又太危险 因为...
it would be rather dangerous because...
这只是个隐喻矛盾 既然谈的是教育 我...
Well, since we were discussing education, I...
感谢上帝
Thank God!
喂? 您的政治顾问来了
Yes? Your political advisor's outside.
请她进来 伯纳 谢谢 汉弗莱      谢谢您
Send her in, Bernard. Humphrey, thank you. Thank you.
你给了我很多值得咀嚼的问题
You've given me much food for thought.
那么 首相 祝您胃口好
In that case, PM, bon app閠it.
亲爱的女士
Dear lady.
什么事 多萝西?
Yes, Dorothy?
关于您西北地区访问的日程
My notes for your tour of the north-west.
您视察医院和工厂的安排 首相
Visits to hospitals and factories.
对 在边缘选区(拉锯战选区)拉选票
Drumming up votes in marginal constituencies.
不行 首相
No!
怎么不行?
Why not?
如果是政府的访问 我就能跟您去
I'm coming with you if it's a government tour.
如果是拉选票 就是党务
If it's canvassing marginals,
我就不能去了 财政部也不报销
I can't come and the Treasury can't pay.
这是政府访问 伯纳
It's a government visit. It's coincidence
只是恰好都定点在边缘选区
that all the stop-offs are in marginals.
那就没问题了      那好
Well, that's all right, then. That's OK.
多萝西 对教育我能做什么? 快一点
What can I do about education? Quickly.
您是要真干 还是显得您在干?
You mean do or appear to do?
显得在干 我当然没法真干
Appear to do. I can't do, obviously.
短期来说 我们可以让您上电视 展示教育成就
we could get you on TV associated with something successful.
好 有机会吗?      我想到一个
Is there something? I had thought of this for your schedule.
您塞进日程吧      圣玛丽学校青年企业计划
You could fit it in. St Margaret's School Young Enterprise Scheme.
对 学校自设制造分销厂
It's set up its own manufacturing company.
制造干酪板 镇纸 吐司架等等
They make cheeseboards, paperweights, toast racks,
自己销售 然后在商业课上追踪整个流程
sell them and track the operation in their business-study classes.
与当地商人合作 还有家长
They involve local businessmen. Parents help.
貌似不错 花销大吗?
Does it cost a lot?
不 还赚钱呢      这不是教孩子唯利是图吗?
Isn't it teaching them to be rather grasping?
不 赚的钱捐给了当地慈善机构
No, they give the money to local charity.
好极了 我要去
Fine, I'll do it.
给电视台安排充足时间拍我...拍摄整个访问
Make sure the TV crews have plenty of time to cover me...
给我写个简短的讲话 20秒 新闻短讯式的
Write me a speech with a snappy, 20-second piece
这能拉到点席位      首相?
That should win back a few seats. PM.
给国民教育的负责人们做点榜样 伯纳
give a lead to those responsible for the nation's education
当然 首相
Of course, PM.
最后 今晨 首相在西北之行的末尾
(NEWSREADER) Finally, the PM visited St Margaret's School
视察了圣玛丽学校
on his north-western tour.
该校自办了一座制造工厂
The school has set up a manufacturing business
孩子们生产各种木工产品 出售给当地社区
where the children make a variety of goods
孩子们自己销售 开拓市场 并以学来的经验
The children do their own sales and marketing
为数学和商业课程打下基础
as a basis for their maths and business studies.
他们赠送给首相一件产品的样品
The PM was presented with an example of the school's output.
总而言之 我要祝贺你们
In conclusion, I must congratulate you
努力的工作 良好的纪律和成功的企业
on the discipline and the success of your enterprise.
你们是英国教育界的楷模
You've set an example in British education
其它学校都该向你们学习
which other schools would do well to follow.
我们需要更多圣玛丽学校
We need more schools like St Margaret's
我会永远珍惜你们的礼物
and I shall always treasure your present.
没有首相会轻易抛弃他的席位
No PM ever lost a seat if he could help itl
这里是BBC六点新闻
(NEWSREADER) And that was the six o'clock news from the BBC.
我觉得还不错 你觉得呢?        很好
I thought that was OK, didn't you? Fine.
我的俏皮话反响不错      是我的俏皮话
My joke went down well. MY joke!
反正比4频道报得好
Better than Channel 4 coverage.
他们没叫它“首相的西北之行”
They didn't describe it as the PM's tour of the north-west.
而叫它“吉姆哈克的边缘选区之行”
They said, "Jim Hacker touring the marginal constituencies."
这是事实 不是吗?
That's true, isn't it?
对 但他们不该明说 这是偏见报道
But they shouldn't say it. It's biased reporting!
报道事实?      访问边缘选区不算错啊
Reporting the facts? Nothing wrong with visiting the marginals.
那他们说的还是事实      明说出来就是有偏见
What they said was still true. It was still biased to say it!
亲爱的 我对你的偏执狂不感兴趣
I'm not interested in your paranoia.
我对那所学校感兴趣
I was interested in that school.
对 父母们排着队想把孩子送进去
Parents queue up to get their children into it.
真遗憾不能全收 来点咖啡?
Pity they can't all get in. Coffee?
太好了      为什么不能多送些孩子进去?
Lovely. Why can't more parents send children there?
没地方了      有啊 学校的数量在下降
No room. There is. School numbers are falling.
那就排挤其它学校了      那又怎样?
That'd mean poaching the other schools. So what?
其它学校没生源 会关门的
The other schools would have to close.
太好了 圣玛丽就能把它们的房子也接管了
Great! St Margaret's could take over their buildings.
亲爱的 这不公平      对谁?
Darling, that wouldn't be fair. Who to?
对那些要关闭的学校里的老师
The teachers in the schools that had to close.
好老师可以去热门学校啊
Good ones could teach at the popular schools.
那差劲老师呢? 对他们不公平
What about the bad teachers? It wouldn't be fair on them.
哪个更重要? 孩子们 还是差劲老师的工作?
are the bad teachers' jobs more important?
亲爱的 这…不太好
Darling, it's... it's no good. Who's to say
谁来评定老师好坏呢? 这行不通
who are the bad teachers? It just wouldn't work.
怎么行不通?      就是行不通
Why not? Well... it wouldn't work.
怎么行不通?      怎么讲?
Why not? What do you mean?
把学校比做大夫 国民保健体系
Suppose schools were like doctors. In the NHS,
允许病人选择大夫 是不是?
you choose which doctor to go to, don't you?
是啊       他按病人人数领薪水
Yes. And he gets paid per patient.
为什么不能对学校也这样呢?
Why don't we do the same with schools?
弄个国民教育体系
Have a National Education Service.
家长选择学校 学校按学生数目来收钱
Parents could choose the schools
太对了      会爆发抗议的
Exactly! There'd be an outcry.
家长吗?      不是家长 是教育部
From the parents? No, from the Department of Education.
好吧 哪方手里选票多?
I see. And who has the most votes?
不行 教育部会封杀它的
The DES would block it.
好啊 除掉他们好了      什么?
Fine, get rid of them. What?
除掉教育部好了      我不明白
Get rid of the Department of Education. I don't understand you.
除掉它 取消它 扔掉它 解除它
Get rid of it, abolish it, remove it, expunge it,
废除它 清除它 根除它
eliminate it, eradicate it, exterminate it!
除掉它      除掉它?
Get rid of it! Get rid of it?
对      我不能这么做
Yes. I couldn't do that.
为什么不能? 它有什么用?      我能做到啊
Why not? What does it do? I could do that.
把事情都交给地方当局
Local government could administer the lot.
设一个学校监察委员会 其它职责交给环境部
We could have a Board of School Inspectors.
然后我就可以把那个
I could send that house-trained
被驯服的白痴大臣扔到上院去
idiot Henry to the House of Lords.
天啊 汉弗莱会怎么说呢
Golly. I wonder what Humphrey will say.
不管他怎么说 我希望亲眼看您告诉他
Whatever he says, I want to be there when you tell him.
来见证政治愿望对抗行政愿望?
the political will and the administrative will?
我想这会是政治愿望对抗行政失望
the political will and the administrative won't.
您找我 首相?        汉弗莱 进来 请坐
You sent for me, PM? Humphrey, come in. Sit down.
我有个新点子问你 我想到怎么改革教育系统了
I've realised how to reform the educational system.
太好了 首相
Excellent, PM.
我准备让家长选择把孩子送到哪所学校去
I'm going to let parents move their children.
您是说 经过申请 审查 聆讯和上诉过程后吗?
after application, scrutiny, tribunal hearing and appeals?
不 想送就送了      对不起 我没听懂
No, just move them whenever they want to.
本届政府将让家长自主决定
This government will let parents decide
把孩子送到哪所学校
which schools to send their children to.
首相 您不是认真的吧
PM, you can't be serious!
我是啊       这也太荒谬了
I am. But it's preposterous!
怎么?      不能指望家长来做决定
Why? You can't expect parents to make these choices.
家长哪知道哪所学校最好呢?
How on earth would parents know which schools are best?
你上的哪所学校 汉弗莱?
Which school did you go to, Humphrey?
温切斯特公学(牛津附中)
Winchester.
它好吗?      学校中的极品
Was it good? Oh, excellent, of course.
谁帮你选的?      自然是我父母
Who chose it? My parents, naturally.
这可不一样 首相 我父母是有鉴察力的人士
Now, that's different, PM. My parents were discerning people.
普通人怎么知道该把孩子送到哪里
ordinary people don't know where to send children.
为什么?      他们怎么分辨?
Why not? Well, how could they tell?
他们自然知道自己的孩子
They could tell if their kids
会不会读写算 学校口碑如何
could read, write and do sums
还有考试成绩好不好
and if the exam results were good.
考试成绩不是一切 首相      没错
Exam results aren't everything. True.
讨厌学院教育的家长 可以把孩子送到特长学校
Parents can pick progressive schools.
可家长没资格做这些选择
But parents have no qualifications to make these choices.
老师都有专业素养 家长最没资格培养孩子了
Parents are the worst people to bring up children.
他们没有认证 没受过训练
They've no qualifications, no training.
教师没有资格不许教书
You don't expect untrained teachers to teach.
家长也应该不许
The same should apply to parents.
生孩子之前 家长应该培训?      不 那不是问题
Before having children, they should be trained?
生孩子的训练人人都受过
They've all been trained to HAVE kids.
性教育课早就成为标准课程了
Sex-education classes have been standard for some years.
是吗 也许我们能改进一下
Perhaps we could do better.
为了生孩子 该让他们通过考试
Before people can have children, we should make them sit exams -
笔试或实践考察
written and practical.
或者两样都考 然后发个养孩子执照
Perhaps both. Then they could be issued with breeding licences.
您真幽默 首相
Oh, very droll, PM.
可我是认真的 家长不合格的是带孩子
It's looking after children that parents are not qualified for.
所以他们不懂得该把孩子送到哪 行不通的
That's why they have no idea which schools to choose
那国民保健呢? 没有医学文凭
What about the Health Service? People choose
人们也能自己选医生
their doctor without medical qualifications.
是啊 那是不一样的      怎么?
Ah, yes, well, that's different. How?
医生么...病人又不是家长 亲爱的女士
Well, doctors are... The patients aren't parents, dear lady.
哦 是吗? 何以见得呢 小汉?
Oh, really? What makes you think that, Humpy?
两码事 话说回来 老实告诉你
Not as such. In any case, as a matter of fact,
我觉得让病人选医生也不对 太混乱了
letting people choose doctors is a very bad idea
把人们交给初诊医生分配更有条理 也更公平
Much tidier to allocate people to GPs, much fairer.
每个人就有同样的机会碰到蹩脚大夫了
Then everyone has an equal chance of getting the bad doctors.
这样啊      总之 我们谈的不是医疗 是教育
I see. In any case, we're talking about education.
恕我直言 首相
With respect, PM,
我认为教育部会对您的新颖建议
I think that the DES will react with some caution
作出谨慎反应的
to your rather novel proposals.
你是说他们会封杀它      他们会慎重考虑
You mean they'll block it. They will give it urgent consideration
并坚决对所有建议作出彻底和严格的审查
insist on a thorough and examination of the proposals
结合详细的可行性研究和预算分析
allied to a detailed feasibility study and budget analysis
拟定一份参考方案 递交各有关部门
producing a consultative document for consideration
请他们作出评论和建议 汇总成一份简报
and seeking comments and recommendations to be included in a brief
送给一系列工作组 分别独立研究
for a series of working parties who will produce individual studies
基于其调查报告 起草一份更加包罗万象的文件
which will provide the background for a more wide-ranging document
据此判定 该建议是否能进入下一步骤
considering whether or not the proposal should be taken forward
你是说他们会封杀它      是啊
You mean they'll block it. Yeah.
没问题      我们早知道你会这么说
No problem. We thought you'd say that.
我们有办法对付      哦 是吗?
We have a solution. Oh, yes?
我们要废除教育部
We'll abolish the DES.
什么?      我们要废除它
I'm sorry? We'll abolish it.
废除?      为什么不?
Abolish it? Why not?
废除教育部?
Abolish Education and Science?!
我们的文明的末日来临了
That'd be the end of civilisation as we know it!
只废除部门 教育还是会兴旺发达的
Only the department. Education will flourish.
没有政府部门管理? 不可能
With no government department? Impossible!
汉弗莱 政府部门好比墓碑
Departments are tombstones.
工业部标志着工业的坟墓
The Department of Industry marks the grave of industry,
就业部是就业的坟墓
the Department of Employment, that of employment,
环境部是环境的坟墓
the Department of Environment, that of the environment.
教育部标志着英国教育的尸体埋葬于此
And the DES marks where the corpse of education is buried.
教育部都干什么? 它扮演什么角色?
What does the DES do? What's its role?
我简直不知从何说起 首相
I hardly know where to begin!
它制订方针政策 它集中拨款
It lays down guidelines, it centralises
分发到教育当局 大学奖学金委员会 它设立标准
and channels money into education authorities  it sets standards!
它设置课程吗?      不 可它很乐意代劳
Does it set the curriculum? It would like to!
选择教研组长?      不...
Select and change head teachers?
维修学校建筑?
Maintain school buildings?
不...      主管考试吗?
No... Set exams?
不...      它选择学生吗?
No... Does it choose the children?
不 可是...      那它怎么影响学校里的孩子呢?
How does it affect what a child does at school?
它提供60％资金
It supplies 60% of the cash.
为什么不能由财政部拨款到学校呢?
Why can't the cash go from the Treasury to the schools?
我们真需要2000名公务员
Do we need 2,000 civil servants
把钱从甲发到乙手上吗?
to funnel money from A to B?
教育部也为教育建立法规制度
The DES also creates a legislative framework for education.
没多少立法吧 环境部就可以做
Not much legislation. Environment could do that.
地方当局还有些事也交给他们
They deal with other local authority matters.
首相 您不是认真的吧
You can't be serious!
那谁来评估发展规划 员工变动 生源变更
Who'd assess forward planning and staffing variations
计划城乡的学校密度呢?
density of schooling required in urban and rural areas?
谁来确保一切正常运转呢?
Who'd make sure everything ran properly?
全国2500所私立学校
2,500 private schools
每天都在自己处理这些 根本不靠教育部
seem to solve these without any help from the DES.
他们能灵活地随机应变
They respond to changing circumstances.
供求关系而已 很简单       那谁计划将来呢?
Supply and demand. It's easy. Who would plan for the future?
这教育现状是教育部计划出来的?
Education today is what the department planned?
当...不 当然不是
Well, of... No, of course not!
教育部还干别的吗?      这...这...
Is there anything else that the DES does? Well, it... it...
好 那我们不需要它了 是吗? 完毕
Well, we don't need it, then, do we? QED.
(拉丁文)证明完毕
Quod erat demonstrandum.
我实在...简直不堪设想
I really... Quite unthinkable.
废除部门的先例一开 文明的基石就垮塌了
Once they start abolishing departments, the civilisation crumble.
野蛮人就会入侵       倒退到黑暗时代
Barbarians at the gates. The return of the Dark Ages.
你当内阁秘书时 爆发过这种危机吗?
Did anything like this crop up when you were Cabinet Secretary?
没有 我们允许他们合并部门 但那没问题
No. We let them amalgamate departments, but that worked very well.
当然了 保留所有的职员
Yes, quite. You keep the existing staff
最高处再加一层统筹领导机构
an extra layer of coordinating management at the top.
正是 但你必须阻止对教育部的清算 汉弗莱
Exactly. But you have to stop the liquidation of the DES
试过抹黑提议者的名声吗?
Have you tried discrediting the person who proposed it?
没用 是那个叫韦莱的女人
No point. It was the Wainwright female,
所以首相当成他自己的主意了
so he's passing it off as his own idea.
扭曲背景事实呢?
Discrediting the facts behind it?
这是个政治主张 所以跟事实无关
It's a political idea, so facts don't come into it.
调整数据?      建议里没数据
Massaging the figures? No figures are involved.
但很难让首相明白 这是个坏主意
But it's hard to get the PM to see that it's a bad idea.
当然 这其实是个好主意 只是不能照办
Of course. It's actually a very good idea. It just mustn't happen.
我不懂我们为什么不能照办
I wonder if we oughtn't to play along with it -
为了全国孩子的利益
in the interests of the nation's children.
管他全国孩子呢
Never mind the nation's children.
我们教育部的同僚怎么办?
What about our colleagues at the DES?
当然 对不起       汉弗莱 我们挑明了说
Of course. Sorry. Let's be clear about this.
唯一会喜欢这主意的就是家长和孩子们
The only people who'll like this idea are the parents
其它有关部门都会反对它
Everyone who counts will be against it.
教师工会      地方当局
Teachers' unions. Local authorities.
教育口的媒体       当然 还有教育部自己
Educational press. And, of course, the DES.
那我们用什么策略?      可以靠工会扰乱学校
Unions can be counted on to disrupt the schools.
然后上电视宣称 是政府导致了混乱
And go on TV saying the government are causing the disruption.
好极了 地方当局会威胁
Good. Local councils will threaten to
发动地方党派反对政府
turn the constituency parties against the government.
好 教育部会拖延每个步骤
The Department of Education will delay every stage of the process
把能让政府难堪的消息都漏出去
and leak anything that embarrasses the government.
我们信息自由运动会助一臂之力的
We can help with that at the Campaign for Freedom of Information.
谢谢 阿诺德
Thank you, Arnold.
啊 谢谢
Ah, thanks.
但我们真正的...谢谢 比利 我们的论点是什么?
But what are we actually... Thank you, Billy. What's our argument?
显然 这项新提议会摧毁我们的教育体系
this new proposal will destroy our educational system.
人人都知道它已经毁了      哦 我们会说...
Everybody knows it's destroyed already. Well, we will say...
对不起 媒体会说
Sorry, the press will say
是政府对教育部的干预摧毁了它
that it's government interference in the DES that destroyed it
而且这个新计划只会雪上加霜
and that this new plan will make things worse.
这样能行吗?      一向有效
Will that do the trick? It always has in the past.
对 但这次是政治压力比较强
But this time the political pressure is stronger.
那你得找件政治武器来对抗
You must find a political weapon to fight it with.
你建议什么政治武器呢 阿诺德?
What political weapon did you have in mind, Arnold?
我? 这是你该操心的了 汉弗莱
I? That is your concern, Humphrey.
是你证明自己
Your chance to prove yourself worthy
担得起如此高位的机会
of the high office to which you've been called.
汉弗莱爵士 首相在等您      什么事?
The PM's ready to see you. What's it about?
恐怕是废除教育部的事      真该死
The abolition of the DES, I'm afraid. This is going to be bloody.
对 有件小事我想先请教您      重要吗 伯纳?
There's a minor matter I need your advice... Is it important?
不重要 但很紧急      快说 什么事?
Not important but urgent. What is it?
您知道首相视察的那所企业学校吗
You know that enterprise school the PM visited,
送他凳子的那所      知道
when they gave him that stool?
刚查出他们工厂的木料...是偷来的
It's just come to light that the wood they were using was stolen.
伯纳 这很难...
Bernard, this is hardly...
偷来的?
Stolen?
对 是政府财产 去年一个青年培训车间里失窃的
Yes, it was government property stolen
万万想不到啊
How shocking.
已经通报教育部了 因为偷窃发生在学校里
It was referred to the DES, as the theft came to light at a school.
他们不知道是否该起诉 很抱歉打扰...
They don't know whether to prosecute. Sorry to bother...
没关系 伯纳
Don't mention it, Bernard.
领我进去
Show me in.
进来 汉弗莱 进来进来 请坐
Come in, Humphrey. Come in, come in! Sit down.
今天只有一项日程——废除教育部
Only one item on the agenda today the abolition of the DES.
实际上 如果只有一件事 那叫议程
Actually, if there's only one item, it's an agenDUM.
我想首相还达不到拉丁文第二变位的程度
I don't think the PM's got as far as the second declension.
我不在乎你强词夺理一回
I don't mind your scoring cheap debating points
反正教育部一役你已经输了
since you've already lost the battle of the DES.
教育部会大发雷霆的 首相
The DES will be very upset.
管它呢 他们就快灭亡了
Does it matter since they'll cease to exist?
解散过程会持续几年 他们会以死相拼的
The process will take a few years. They'll fight tooth and nail.
他们能把我怎样?      他们是个令人生畏的部门
What can they do to me? They're a formidable department.
我是个令人生畏的首相      您确实是 首相
I am a formidable PM. Indeed you are.
但您也许还需要他们的合作
But you might still need their cooperation.
合作? 教育部的? 别开玩笑了
Cooperation? From the Department of Education? Don't make me laugh!
好吧 好吧 那我就由他们去起诉了
Fine, fine. I'll tell them to go ahead with the prosecution, then.
什么起诉?        哦 这点小事不值得打扰您
What prosecution? Oh, it's hardly worth bothering you with.
就是上周电视上 您视察的企业学校
That enterprise school where you were televised last week.
怎么?      那些利润...其它学校的楷模...
Yes? The profits... A model for other schools...
是 是 然后呢
Yes, yes, go on.
利润似乎是偷窃来的       什么偷窃?
The profits were the proceeds of theft. Theft?
就是在物主不知道或不许可的情况下取走物品...
I mean removing goods without the knowledgeof the owner...
我知道偷窃的意思 你是什么意思?
I know what theft means. What do YOU mean?
哦 他们送您的凳子
Well, the stool that they gave you
是用偷来的木头做的 来自当地的青年培训车间
was made from wood appropriated from the local YTS workshops.
你是什么意思?      顺出来的
What do you mean? It was nicked.
两名去年的学生干的
By two of last year's pupils.
人赃俱获       谢谢 伯纳
A pair of nickers. Thank you, Bernard.
青年培训车间想要起诉
The YTS want to prosecute.
只有教育部可以阻止他们
Now, the Department of Education could stop them.
您知道 把木料归还 就不声张了
You know, return the wood and hush it up.
汉弗莱 几百万人看到我在电视上
Millions saw me on TV saying
说那学校是全英的楷模
that school was an example!
也算是某种楷模
Well, it is a sort of example.
汉弗莱 他们决不能起诉
They mustn't prosecute!
但愿教育部不会向媒体漏消息
I hope the Department of Education won't leak
说您包庇偷窃行为
the fact that you're covering up for crooks.
你得告诉他们别起诉      那需要他们的配合
You must tell them not to. need their cooperation.
我都能看到报纸头条了 “吉姆的小偷公司”
I can just see the newspapers "Jim's enterprising crooks.
"昔日首相骑墙头 今日落进大墙里"
"The PM has sat on the fence for so long that now he's become one."
劝他们别起诉啊
Persuade them not to prosecute.
已经被判死刑的人可不太听劝
It's very difficult to persuade if they are under a death sentence.
死刑?      您不是要废这个部吗?
Death sentence? If you're abolishing the department.
那个啊
Oh, that!
不 那只是个...模糊的想法...
No, that was just... a vague idea...
...多萝西的
...of Dorothy's.
随便想想 不是认真的
An idle thought. Nothing serious.
您确定吗?      当然了
You're sure? Positive.
太好了 首相 可以谈今天的议程了吗?
Splendid, PM. Shall we now continue with the agendum?
议程? 哦 对
Agendum? Oh, yes!
我们没议程
We have no agendum.
我 们 今 天 没 议 程
(RHYTHMICALLY) We have no agendum today!
本案结束 好吗 汉弗莱?
Business concluded. All right, Humphrey?
是 首相
Yes, PM.
-==www.RagBear.com==- 破烂熊字幕组 欢迎加入